Before seeing how far this idea can
go, let us address a natural question.
Where in this hierarchy does the continuum fit?
The Continuum Hypothesis, which Cantor believed but was unable to
prove and we will soon see why, states that size
of the continuum is the next infinity after omega.
If the CH is false, then there are sets of
intermediate size, greater than the size of the natural numbers,
but smaller than the set of real numbers.
And the Generalized continuum hypothesis, asserts that the power
set of any cardinal is the next cardinal.
We will do a whole video on the CH soon, as it is the
first statement which was formally shown to be independent from the axioms of ZFC.
Meaning that if we feed the ZFC axioms into our theorem prover,
it will never spit out a proof of CH nor its negation.
For now, let us just assume for simplicity that the GCH holds,
and let us see how far this infinite hierarchy can go.
Now we can surely continue performing this
procedure all the way to aleph omega.
Recall that we were originally trying to define a Universe of sets. I.e.
some set which satisfies each of the ZFC axioms. Now, if we cut
off the universe at aleph omega, we would obtain a model of a
lot of ZFC, but the axiom of Replacement would fail.
Since we can define a function which
maps natural numbers n to aleph_n.
By the axiom of replacement the range
of this function should be a set.
And by the axiom of union, so should its union.
But the union of the range of this
function is V_omega itself, and equals aleph omega.
But V_omega cannot contain aleph_omega.
So, we don't yet have a model of set theory.
We have to continue further. But the cat is already out of
the bag, we have already accepted the existence of transfinite numbers, so
we can continue beyond V_omega just as we did before.
We can define aleph omega plus one, and
eventually aleph omega one and so on.
Now if we look at the generalization of this function here, which
sends an ordinal alpha to aleph_alpha, we see that this is an
increasing continuous function on the ordinals, and so by the fixed point
theorem, there is a fixed point which we will call kappa.
So kappa equals aleph kappa.
If kappa is also a so-called regular cardinal
then V_kappa is a model of ZFC.
Meaning that it is a Universe of sets.
However, by Godel's completeness theorem, this
means that ZFC is consistent.
But then this implies that we cannot prove the
existence of such a cardinal kappa, since if we
could then we would have a proof of the
consistency of ZFC, which contradicts Godel's second incompleteness theorem.